<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>RSE at Sheffield (Posts about careers)</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/categories/careers.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 10:58:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>RSE Career Paths and a Vacancy in the RSE Team</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/rse-career-paths-and-a-vacancy-in-the-rse-team/</link><dc:creator>Paul Richmond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the key motivations, shared by myself and Mike Croucher, for establishing an RSE group at the University of Sheffield was to provide a career path for RSEs. The RSE team has been working for some time with HR on establishing a generic job (role) description for G7 and G8 (lecturer level) RSEs which can be used for staff progression. I am please to announce that these are now &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/community/job-descriptions"&gt;published on our website&lt;/a&gt;. The job descriptions provide a template for the recruitment of RSEs across the whole university and are the job descriptions which members of the RSE team work from. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conjunction with the release of these RSE job descriptions &lt;strong&gt;I am excited to announce that we are currently advertising an open-ended RSE position to join the RSE group&lt;/strong&gt;. This is particularly important to me as the group director as it is the first &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; open-ended RSE post to be advertised which is not attached to any particular research project. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/rse-career-paths-and-a-vacancy-in-the-rse-team/#open_ended_footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The significance of this is that this role demonstrates that the university is bought into the RSE vision and strategy which has been developed at Sheffield. A large number of people have contributed to developing this strategy and I am extremely pleased to see it moving forward. The new position will be working within a &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/contact/team"&gt;group of RSEs&lt;/a&gt; which has grown significantly over the last two years (additional recruitment is planned shortly). Myself and the group look forward to welcoming a new candidate into the team. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://jobs.shef.ac.uk/sap/bc/webdynpro/sap/hrrcf_a_posting_apply?PARAM=cG9zdF9pbnN0X2d1aWQ9NUJCQzAwMEQ0ODI4MTVGQUUxMDAwMDAwQUMxRTg4NzgmY2FuZF90eXBlPUVYVA%3d%3d&amp;amp;sap-client=400&amp;amp;sap-language=EN&amp;amp;sap-accessibility=X&amp;amp;sap-ep-themeroot=%2fSAP%2fPUBLIC%2fBC%2fUR%2fuos#"&gt;Follow this link for the job advert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/BNJ857/research-software-engineer-rse"&gt;jobs.ac.uk advert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Informal questions relating to this post or any other matter can be directed to myself (Paul Richmond) via the RSE website &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/contact"&gt;contact&lt;/a&gt; details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="open_ended_footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;: The University of Sheffield RSE strategy has enabled current RSE team members to transition into open-ended positions from fixed term contracts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>careers</category><category>jobs</category><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/rse-career-paths-and-a-vacancy-in-the-rse-team/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 11:55:39 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>