<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>RSE at Sheffield (Posts by Mozhgan Kabiri Chimeh)</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/authors/mozhgan-kabiri-chimeh.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 10:58:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Coffee and Cakes Event</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/coffee-and-cakes-event-2nd/</link><dc:creator>Mozhgan Kabiri Chimeh</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;RSE Sheffield is hosting another coffee and cakes event on &lt;strong&gt;May 31st at 14:00 in the Ada Lovelace room&lt;/strong&gt; on 1st floor of the Computer Science Department (Regents Court East). Attendance is free, but you need to register via &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/forms/L2dRQNvSUvkIbtSm2"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the opportunity to come and have an informal chat about research software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event is a community event for anyone, not just computer science or members of the RSE team. If you work on software development are an RSE or simply want to talk about some aspect of software or software in teaching then come along.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/coffee-and-cakes-event-2nd/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 11:12:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A new member of the team: Mozhgan Kabiri Chimeh</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/mozhgankch_intro/</link><dc:creator>Mozhgan Kabiri Chimeh</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;My name is &lt;strong&gt;Mozhgan Kabiri Chimeh&lt;/strong&gt; and I am a &lt;a href="https://rse.ac.uk/"&gt;Research Associate/Research Software Engineer&lt;/a&gt; who specialises in performance acceleration targeting Many-core and Multi-core architectures. Research is my passion and I have carefully developed my education with research and teaching in mind. I completed my PhD in computer science in 2016 at the University of Glasgow where my area of research was accelerating logic gate circuit simulation targeting heterogeneous architectures.  As part of my PhD project, I optimised and accelerated simulation algorithms and applied them to various parallel architectures (SIMD enabled machines, clusters, and GPUs). I have practical experience with parallel programming using High Performance Computing languages and models including OpenMP and CUDA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am glad to be a part of RSE team as well as working as a researcher in Computer Graphic and simulation modelling group here at the University of Sheffield. Feel free to get in touch with me via my email address (m.kabiri-chimeh (at) sheffield.ac.uk) or my &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mozhgankch"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When not working I divide my time between family, movie, artwork and macro-photography!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/mozhgankch_intro/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 08:09:22 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>