<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>RSE at Sheffield (Posts by Paul Richmond)</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/authors/paul-richmond.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 10:58:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>RSE Career Paths and a Vacancy in the RSE Team</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/rse-career-paths-and-a-vacancy-in-the-rse-team/</link><dc:creator>Paul Richmond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the key motivations, shared by myself and Mike Croucher, for establishing an RSE group at the University of Sheffield was to provide a career path for RSEs. The RSE team has been working for some time with HR on establishing a generic job (role) description for G7 and G8 (lecturer level) RSEs which can be used for staff progression. I am please to announce that these are now &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/community/job-descriptions"&gt;published on our website&lt;/a&gt;. The job descriptions provide a template for the recruitment of RSEs across the whole university and are the job descriptions which members of the RSE team work from. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conjunction with the release of these RSE job descriptions &lt;strong&gt;I am excited to announce that we are currently advertising an open-ended RSE position to join the RSE group&lt;/strong&gt;. This is particularly important to me as the group director as it is the first &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; open-ended RSE post to be advertised which is not attached to any particular research project. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/rse-career-paths-and-a-vacancy-in-the-rse-team/#open_ended_footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The significance of this is that this role demonstrates that the university is bought into the RSE vision and strategy which has been developed at Sheffield. A large number of people have contributed to developing this strategy and I am extremely pleased to see it moving forward. The new position will be working within a &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/contact/team"&gt;group of RSEs&lt;/a&gt; which has grown significantly over the last two years (additional recruitment is planned shortly). Myself and the group look forward to welcoming a new candidate into the team. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://jobs.shef.ac.uk/sap/bc/webdynpro/sap/hrrcf_a_posting_apply?PARAM=cG9zdF9pbnN0X2d1aWQ9NUJCQzAwMEQ0ODI4MTVGQUUxMDAwMDAwQUMxRTg4NzgmY2FuZF90eXBlPUVYVA%3d%3d&amp;amp;sap-client=400&amp;amp;sap-language=EN&amp;amp;sap-accessibility=X&amp;amp;sap-ep-themeroot=%2fSAP%2fPUBLIC%2fBC%2fUR%2fuos#"&gt;Follow this link for the job advert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/BNJ857/research-software-engineer-rse"&gt;jobs.ac.uk advert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Informal questions relating to this post or any other matter can be directed to myself (Paul Richmond) via the RSE website &lt;a href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/contact"&gt;contact&lt;/a&gt; details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="open_ended_footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;: The University of Sheffield RSE strategy has enabled current RSE team members to transition into open-ended positions from fixed term contracts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>careers</category><category>jobs</category><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/rse-career-paths-and-a-vacancy-in-the-rse-team/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 11:55:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Research Software Engineer in High Performance Computing</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/research_software_engineer_in_high_performance_computing/</link><dc:creator>Paul Richmond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A job opportunity within the RSE Sheffield group is available under the job title of "Research Software Engineer in High Performance Computing (HPC) enabled Multi-Scale Modelling".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the Research Software Engineer post is to enhance The University’s capability and expertise in developing Research Software. This role will be based in the newly formed &lt;a href="https://rse.shef.ac.uk/"&gt;Research Software Engineering group&lt;/a&gt;, which aims to improve all aspects of research software including reproducibility, usability, efficiency and correctness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary function of this role is to support the EC funded CompBioMed project. A user-driven Centre of Excellence in Computational Biomedicine, to nurture and promote the uptake and exploitation of high performance computing within the biomedical modelling community. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post is fixed-term with an end date of 30 September 2019. The deadline for applications is 19th June 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Links and More Information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jobs.ac.uk/job/BBN749/research-software-engineer-in-high-performance-computing-hpc-enabled-multi-scale-modelling"&gt;Jobs.ac.uk posting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://jobs.shef.ac.uk/sap/bc/webdynpro/sap/hrrcf_a_posting_apply?PARAM=cG9zdF9pbnN0X2d1aWQ9MzMwNjJBRkQ4MDQ5MUVFNzhGOEY4MkE0ODgzRjg4MEYmY2FuZF90eXBlPUVYVA%3d%3d&amp;amp;sap-client=400&amp;amp;sap-language=EN&amp;amp;sap-accessibility=X&amp;amp;sap-ep-themeroot=%2fSAP%2fPUBLIC%2fBC%2fUR%2fuos#"&gt;University of Sheffield Application Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>jobs</category><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/research_software_engineer_in_high_performance_computing/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2017 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building Linux GPU Code with NSIGHT in Windows</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/building-linux-gpu-code-with-nsight-in-windows/</link><dc:creator>Paul Richmond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why would you possibly want to build and execute CUDA GPU applications within NSight Eclipse for Linux within Microsoft Windows? Well if you use windows as your main OS there are plenty of reasons but the most obvious is that you may be developing cross platform code and want to build and test it without dual booting. If you are thinking about virtual machines then forget about it. Most (except some very expensive enterprise options) do not have the ability to access a GPU device (e.g GPU pass-through) from within a virtual machine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is to describe how to install the necessary tools to permit local GPU development inside the Linux NSight IDE from within Windows. The advantages of which are not only cross platform development but also the ability to locally develop in powerful Linux IDE with remote execution and graphical debugging. This is particularly helpful if you want to execute or debug your code on a HPC system (like Sheffield's ShARC system) from Windows. The post focuses on the use of the new Windows 10 Linux subsystem, however you could use the approach to install CUDA tools on a lightweight Linux virtual machine. The concept is the same either way. i.e. build and debug locally execute remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Configuring the Linux Windows Subsystem for CUDA compilation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Windows 10 subsystem for Linux is available in the anniversary update. You can install it from the "Turn on or off windows features" dialogue. It is listed under "Windows subsystem for Linux (beta)". This alone is not enough to build our GPU applications as we will need to install CUDA. A normal CUDA install will require a local GPU and the installation of a CUDA compatible graphics driver. Fire up the Windows Bash Shell (or a Linux virtual machine). You can then use the following commands to install the CUDA toolkit without installing a graphics driver. This will install the core NVIDIA CUDA compiler (nvcc) and NSight. You can update the &lt;code&gt;CUDA_REPO_PKG&lt;/code&gt; variable to install a different CUDA version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo apt-get update
CUDA_REPO_PKG=cuda-repo-ubuntu1404_8.0.44-1_amd64.deb
wget http://developer.download.nvidia.com/compute/cuda/repos/ubuntu1404/x86_64/$CUDA_REPO_PKG
sudo dpkg -i $CUDA_REPO_PKG
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install -y --no-install-recommends cuda-core-8-0 cuda-cudart-dev-8-0 nsight
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can now create a symbolic link to a generic CUDA install. This will permit the addition and fast swapping of different CUDA versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo ln -s /usr/local/cuda-8.0 /usr/local/cuda 
export PATH=$PATH:/usr/local/cuda/bin
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note: if you want the CUDA bin location to be persistently on the PATH (after you reboot the Bash shell) then you will need to add the &lt;code&gt;export PATH&lt;/code&gt; line to your .bashrc profile. Test that the install was successful by running nvcc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;nvcc --version
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This should give you some information on the nvcc version. e.g. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;nvcc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NVIDIA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Cuda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;compiler&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;driver&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Copyright&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2005&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2016&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NVIDIA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Corporation&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Built&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Tue_Jan_10_13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_CST_2017&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Cuda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;compilation&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tools&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;release&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;8.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;V8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.61&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The CUDA toolkit is now installed so you can build (but not execute) CUDA GPU programs using the Linux bash shell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Graphical editing with Nsight IDE&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be able to run a graphical NSight IDE from within the Windows subsystem for Linux you will need to be running a X server within Windows. You can install the &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/xming/"&gt;XMing&lt;/a&gt; application for this purpose. If you would rather use a Linux virtual machine then you can avoid this step as the virtual machine will most likely have an X server included. The advantage of the Windows subsystem approach is that it is very lightweight. From within your Bash terminal you will need to set the following environment variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;export DISPLAY=:0
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The display variable is an environment variable passed to graphical applications. In this case, the value of &lt;code&gt;:0&lt;/code&gt; it tells the application to use the first display on the local system (our XMing server in this case). If you want to make this environment variable change permanent then you should add it to your .bashrc profile. You can now run the NSight application from Bash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;nsight
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Glorious isn't it. Within NSight we can create a new CUDA project which will compile using the local CUDA install. In order to remotely execute and debug you can use the "C++ Remote application" run configuration. This will require SSH access to a suitable Linux machine with a GPU and CUDA installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future blog posts will cover how remote execution and debugging can be achieved on the University of Sheffield ShARC system. ShARC has a typical of job based HPC system which encourages job submission rather than execution of code on worker nodes via SSH logins. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Summary of Bash Profile Changes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I added the following to my .bashrc profile (located in the home directory) to ensure that NSight could be launched straight after starting the Bash shell in Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;# add cuda bin dir to path
export PATH=$PATH:/usr/local/cuda/bin

# export the display environment variable
export DISPLAY=:0
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/building-linux-gpu-code-with-nsight-in-windows/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 16:03:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Coffee and Cakes Event</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/coffee-and-cakes-event/</link><dc:creator>Paul Richmond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;RSE Sheffield is hosting its first coffee and cakes event on &lt;strong&gt;4th October 2016 at 10:00 in the Ada Lovelace&lt;/strong&gt; room on 1st floor of the Computer Science Department (Regents Court East). Attendance is free and you don't need to register (or bring coffee and cake with you). Simply call in and take the opportunity to come and have an informal chat about research software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event is a community event for anyone not just computer science or members of the RSE team. If you work on software development are an RSE or simply want to talk about some aspect of software or software in teaching then come along.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/coffee-and-cakes-event/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2016 14:42:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The University of Sheffield named an NVIDIA GPU Education Center</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/the-university-of-sheffield-named-an-nvidia-gpu-education-center/</link><dc:creator>Paul Richmond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/NVIDIA_education.jpg" alt="Sheffield NVIDIA Education Centre" align="right" width="20%"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I am very pleased to announce that the University of Sheffield has been awarded the status of an NVIDIA CUDA Education Centre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The faculty of Engineering has featured this in its latest &lt;a href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/faculty/engineering/news/nvidia-1.587003"&gt;faculty newsletter&lt;/a&gt; and the Department of Computer Science has published more details in a &lt;a href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/dcs/latest-news/nvidia-1.587214"&gt;news feature&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;But what does this mean to the RSE community at Sheffield and beyond?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recognition of being an NVIDIA education centre is a reflection of the teaching that is provided by The University of Sheffield on the subject of GPU computing. In case you are unaware of what teaching there is, I have a 4th year and Masters teaching module &lt;a href="http://paulrichmond.shef.ac.uk/teaching/COM4521/"&gt;COM4521/COM6521&lt;/a&gt; which ran for the first time in the 2015/2016 Spring Semester. This course will be run annually and is open to research staff as well as taught students. Last time there was roughly a 50:50 mix including senior research staff and PhD students. It is much more involved that the one or two day courses which typically give only an introduction to GPU programming. If you are a researcher looking to exploit GPU performance in your research then this course is an opportunity to learn some new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future this course will be made freely available so even researchers outside of The University of Sheffield will be able to go through the notes and worked examples (lab sheets). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the other benefits of being an NVIDIA Eduction (and also an NVIDIA Research) centre are;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to NVIDIA GPU hardware and software (via Iceberg and in the Diamond labs) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Significant discount on Tesla hardware purchases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to NVIDIA parallel programming experts and resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to educational webinars and an array of teaching materials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free in the cloud GPU programming training at &lt;a href="https://nvidia.qwiklab.com/"&gt;nvidia.qwiklab.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support in the form of letters of support (with contributions in kind) for research proposals with emphasis on GPU computing or deep learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joint promotion, public relations, and press activities with NVIDIA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other Training Opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through &lt;a href="https://rse.shef.ac.uk/"&gt;RSE Sheffield&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://gpucomputing.sites.sheffield.ac.uk"&gt;GPUComputing@Sheffield&lt;/a&gt; shorter courses for GPU computing are also available. I will be announcing dates for 1-2 day CUDA courses shortly and am working with CICS in developing new Python CUDA material. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those that missed the sign-up, we are also running a two day deep learning with GPUs course in July. The places for this were in high demand and filled up within a day. This course will be repeated in due time and material from the course will be made available off-line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other GPU announcements will be made on both this RSE blog and on the &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/a/sheffield.ac.uk/forum/#!forum/gpucomputing"&gt;GPUComputing@Sheffield mailing list&lt;/a&gt;. Expect some exciting new hardware and software once the Iceberg upgrade is complete (shortly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/the-university-of-sheffield-named-an-nvidia-gpu-education-center/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2016 16:50:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>We're hiring - RSE Position on Massive Scale Complex Systems Simulation with Accelerated Computing</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/RSE_gpu_role_2016/</link><dc:creator>Paul Richmond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new position is available as a Research Associate/Research Software Engineer in the area of complex systems modelling using emerging high performance parallel architectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post can be configured in two different ways. Either as a 3 year Research Associate/Research Software Engineer only, or as a 5 year post working as a Research Associate/Research Software Engineer (60%) and a Research Software Consultant (40%). Candidate’s preference for either option will be discussed at the interview stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://jobs.shef.ac.uk/sap/bc/webdynpro/sap/hrrcf_a_posting_apply?PARAM=cG9zdF9pbnN0X2d1aWQ9NTcxNUQzNTRGNTJCNkM5OEUxMDAwMDAwQUMxRTg4NzgmY2FuZF90eXBlPUVYVA%3d%3d&amp;amp;sap-client=400&amp;amp;sap-language=EN&amp;amp;sap-accessibility=X&amp;amp;sap-ep-themeroot=%2fSAP%2fPUBLIC%2fBC%2fUR%2fuos#"&gt;The University of Sheffield job site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/RSE_gpu_role_2016/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 09:06:12 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>